[Music]
hello guy P Journey how are you hey
Simon I'm good I'm excited pumped to uh
to get AI native Devcon underway
absolutely very excited
absolutely so for those who for those
who don't know guy P what can I what can
I say about guy that perhaps won't get
me fired of need to like start by
lowering expectations always is like
great start of it okay indeed so I'm Geo
Journey or GPO I am the founder and CEO
of tessle and I'm fairly known for
founding sneak uh before that and a few
other things uh and I'm going to give a
bit of an intro to AI native software
development and how we perceive it
wonderful well guy without further Ado
I'll hand the stage over to you and uh I
hope everyone enjoys the session sounds
good well thanks everybody for tuning in
as I said I'm really excited for us to
kick off AI native Devcon uh we really
think of ai's implication on software
development implications as massive uh
and we think it's a it's a group effort
if you will it's a community activity we
want us all to uh collaborate and
discuss how uh do we want software
development to evolve and so really
excited we're going to continue to
invest as tessel uh in in this community
and in in making it an easy place to
share learnings to share tools and such
I'll talk about that a bit more uh I
today am going to talk a little bit
about how we see AI native software
development uh and you know a little bit
of of our the journey that we see ahead
for community and for Tesla itself so if
you think about software development uh
It software development Journey has
always been kind of around making
software development easier and
therefore more in inclusive you know
we've gone from like punch cards in
which it was very much not inclusive you
had to know a lot but also uh be willing
to invest the time and have access to
these machines into assembly that uh
required a sophistication and sort of
power and a lot of patience to be able
to develop in but was very powerful you
could do a lot of things onto C
C++ easier to build easier to create and
therefore more developers come into the
fold uh many at the time were
complaining that you have to go down to
assembly if you want to really control
it right and continue into Java and
JavaScript same narratives every time
you make it easier to create and
therefore you bring in more people into
the fold and part of the trade-off of
here is that you had to give up some
amount of control to be able to get that
ease of use so just a few examples here
if you think about C for instance you
know you this is a little small example
that opens up a file and counts the
number of Lines within it you know you
have a lot of control in how you're
going to do it but there's a lot of like
Voodoo words over here that you have to
really understand file pointers and
fopen and you're creating buffers in
memory you're going to read stuff into
you have to manage them correctly so a
lot of control not like much easier than
assembly and such before uh but a lot of
risk is involved as well if you go to
Java you know if you see the evolution
uh it's not less verbose Java is not
known for brevity shall we say uh but
you have uh much easier to understand
like things that are more English
language buffered reader and file reader
and read line it also is a lot safer
it's surrounded a lot of choices have
kind of moved to the system and they
will not allow you to override memory or
things like that and they force you to
create exception so safer environment a
little bit less control that continues
into to higher level languages and
script languages like Python and
JavaScript that really start resembling
English language but really at this
point you really have uh a lot less
control about how things are done memory
allocation the choice of uh file opening
the choice of defaults a lot of those
things go away and but but it's a lot
easier it's a lot easier to
create and llms really offer us sort of
this opportunity to take this to the
next level and say hey just just use
English or actually another language
just use natural language and say hey
just print the number of lines in
example txt and that's amazing that that
is very much on the trajectory of
software Evolution and we want that but
it's also um uh risky a little bit
because llms really make us give up a
lot of control and sometimes maybe too
much control and the question is can we
can we tap this sort of magic this power
so we leverage the sort of this ease of
use this this leverage this ability to
create a lot with few words but we
retain control right and we know that
when we say print the number of lines uh
in example txt it doesn't just print
those words but rather the meaning we
don't have really any measures for that
today to be able to think about how we
do that we have to think a bit about
software development from first
principles so let's talk about two
things around software development today
one is that code couples today what the
application does or software does and
how it does it this is a small example
uh if you look a little bit of this
function that is intentionally not named
maybe take a few seconds try to think
what is this application doing you can
see the how you can see the the for Loop
the counting of it I won't waste too
much of your time you might have
realized during this time that this is a
sort function uh and it takes an array
and it sorts it and okay that's uh
that's all good and well
uh as you do it but first of all it's a
bit of an indication so you had to
deduce the what the application does
from the code and the code also decides
both what is being done and how is it
done and we rely on these uh symbolic
these descriptive traits like the
function names and the comments to
understand the code and understand what
it does and I think anybody that has a
little bit of mileage in software
development has already encountered many
times cases where that is just
absolutely not the case you see
functions that are not correctly named
sometimes hard to name them you see
comments that are missing because
there's no functional uh imperative to
actually make those
correct let's continue this example and
think about this function this is also a
sort function the what of what it does
is the same as the previous function
they both sort the uh the array that
they get but this one does it through
merge sort it's a different algorithm
they're both legit selection sort is a
little simpler to understand and it uses
less memory but it's less efficient
while merge sort is fast but it does a
lot of recursion a lot of memory so
they're both legit options but they
really demonstrate that there could be
multiple hows to the same what and if
you stumble upon this code you really
don't have any indications as to what
was the requirement that uh that came in
in the first place so you look at this
and say well someone chose merge sord so
chose
selection why was that just a whim of
this developer or was it an intentional
Choice uh that met the requirements if
it was intentional and based on the data
is that still relevant like is that
still the correct data have we got more
data now have we got less data are
multiple people using the same function
multiple functions using this utility
function if you uh drill a bit deeper
you would notice that if if you use sort
of a string arrays over here you will
get a case sensitive sort is that on
purpose or is that just sort of a bug or
an implementation decision that has
never been stated all of those now
become a fact of the application all of
that truth sits in the code and the code
ends up describing both the what the
application does how it behaves and how
it is
implemented this led software
development to be very code Centric if
you think about software development
today you can say simplistically that it
takes some requirements it goes on to
produce some code then you take that
code you package it up so people can use
it and then hopefully you invest some
time in documenting and creating test
audience I say hopefully because again
not mandatory there's no immediate uh
thing immediate feedback loop immediate
problem that happens if you don't
properly document it or don't create
tests for
it over time the only thing that really
kind of truly stands the test of time is
the code the requirements come along you
write the code the odds of you being
able to find those requirements two
years later are fairly low three years
later four year L four years later the
the code continue the code continues and
becomes the source of truth of the
application that's the thing that we
decorate the packages clearly it's a
buil output we build it we build it we
don't have any precious element to it
and the documentation and the tests
they're partial they don't represent the
application well the code continues and
it gets heavier and heavier over time
enhancements come along they expand the
code they add more to it bug fixes come
along and they add small bits in various
places edge cases maybe add like ifs and
weird things into the code that are not
quite elegant but they address a problem
that a customer might have had ecosystem
changes might really Force us to do sort
of unnatural things in uh in in software
upgrades and things like that all of
those make the code messy the code
becomes big it's hard to hold in your
head we start talking about onboarding
developers and how do we kind of make
them understand the code to deal with
that we get into refactoring projects
that are expensive to it to make things
worse the docs and the tests which are
not like functionally connected to the
code they're not necessary for the
application to work just for software
developments to work well in consumption
they follow by the wayside they get out
of date over time changes to the
software become risky and will become
risk averse every time you change you
might have some of that refactoring work
on it you might have more tests you're
you're trying to judge whether or not
changes are worth it they're worth the
risk and and really maintenance of the
software for changes that you have to do
becomes a a big burden new operating
systems new dependencies changes to
Services you have to do the that work
each one of these changes is risky and
expensive and pretty kind of within a
few years within some amount of time
pretty much every software project gets
to the state in which a big chunk of the
development team's time is spent on
keeping the lights on on maintaining the
software the pace reduces for a variety
of reasons including the complexity of
the code this isn't like I'm not
knocking anybody by saying this this is
just the inevitability almost of
software development over
time AI Dev tools come along and today
they they help they're significant you
know I'm big big fan of a lot of these
AI Dev tools we use a lot of them when
we develop software a tessel and a sneak
and highly recommend that you do but
they don't really change any of this
broader picture what they do is they
make the lines better they make the
lines faster it's easier and faster to
create code for enhancements for bug
fixes for edge cases for all of for
migrations it's also easier to tackle
the toil the the docks the test it's
easier to maintain those so they keep
those lines straight but they don't
change the fundamental the only thing
that stays are is the code The Prompt
that created them all of that user
experience uh new user experience to
create code that is what it does it you
you give it language you interact with
it and it creates more code in fact some
claim that they create too much codes
too quickly and they actually increase
the maintenance burden because many of
them are great at creating the code but
they don't actually take responsibility
for maintaining it over
time so this is great but it doesn't
solve the problem and we think we can
actually solve the problem or we can
make step change by rethinking the
workflow we think that llms allow us to
decouple what the application does from
how it does it and this is for a few
reasons first is the two are first are
more obvious the first is that uh it's
easier than ever to say what it is that
you want you don't need sort of formal
structures and things like that you can
use language you can use mockups you can
use visuals you can interact verbally
with the system it's easier than ever to
talk to machines to to express what you
want there's a lot of unknowns around it
we'll talk about that in a sec but it's
much easier than before and that
combines with the fact that machines can
write code now and so in the combination
of it's easier for you to say what you
want and it is the machine is able to
write that code that's a magical
combination and that's what we're seeing
also in a lot of these you know claw or
chpt when you go off and you create an
application the third thing that is not
really discussed is that llms can fill
in the gaps and I think that is a
massive unlock and doesn't get enough
attention you can go to the L and say
create a tictac toe game without
explaining the rules of tictac toe this
is different than what you could do in
previous specifications up until the
llms come along up until this era of AI
every time you wanted software to do
something you had to explain every
little bit and the only places where you
didn't have to is places where a problem
was entirely solved by something
underneath like memory management in
Java but those were very limited because
you you confined yourself only to these
building blocks that have already been
already been created in this sort of
vast world of of human knowledge you
have to specify every time all the
different details and llms break that
mold llms enable us to say create the
tic tac toe game and know the rules and
over time they can get better at better
or rather platforms that use llms can
get better and better at filling in
those gaps if you think about an agency
that you work with that has built five
marketing websites for you if you come
to them and you say build a sixth one
you need to give them a very small spec
because they know you they know the the
domain they build marketing websites
they do that for a living they've done
it for a long time so they know what
they need to do you don't need to tell
them everything if this is the first
time you work with that agency you
probably need to tell them more the spec
needs to be a bit bigger because they
don't know you if they've never built a
marketing website before you probably
need to give them even more
specification same goes if you go to
some sort of lowcost agency that really
you know you don't trust as much their
execution you just want the sheer
Firepower and the same is true for these
llms you train the llms so that they get
better at knowing you at knowing a
domain a type of application and so they
become more like the best the most
senior developer on your team that you
have to give little specification to
them to build something versus the most
Junior one on the
team all of these combine to really say
that uh llms make specs practical they
take specs that used to be kind of very
poorly structured hard to build overly
detailed uh and limited in what they
could create to building blocks that
have been pre-aged to something that is
flexible that can fill in the gaps and
we think that is massively powerful and
it allows us to think of a transition
from code Centric software development
to spec Centric software development and
so instead of AC crewing the changes
over time to the code instead of
enhancements and Bug fixes and edge
cases ecosystem changes all of those
acing to the code to the implementation
those changes ACR to the requirements
and the requirement ments represent what
the system does over time to strengthen
that you also pair up the requirement
with the tests and you put all of those
in this specification so the spec now
says what the system does and has some
examples some assurances a lot to say
about that that help verify that the
software indeed does as it should only
to the degree that you care about you
might want a button you might not care
about its color so it would verify to
the level that the spec
cares Not only would it generate the
code this approach also allows all of
these anciliary objects these
descriptive objects to actually become
generated objects documentation software
bill of materials all sorts of
attestations about what has occurred
mocks API documentations all of those
can stay up to speed because they become
a part of the software always verified
always vetted against that
spec we call this sort of new paradigm
of spec Centric development AI native
software development uh and we think it
is very powerful we think there's a lot
of uh a lot there are many advantages
that this can bring let's talk about a
few of the key
ones the first one is that you always
know what the software does this is kind
of in the name of spec Centric
development when you think about code
Centric you're going to come along as we
just discussed you might change
something you might go from the merge
sort to the quick sort and you might you
know change the color of a button and in
the process of that you might be
changing what the application does if
even without intending to do so and you
know that that is uh that is just by by
the nature of the Beast because there's
actually no place for you to update
except maybe these ancillary docks that
are not functional to say what is it
that you have changed and so it's very
likely that you break that in the spec
Centric mode mode every change every
change that you make every every pathway
that might modify the code first vets
that the spec continues to to be adhered
to and so you know any time that the
spec is always systematically applied to
the code you know what the system does a
closely related behavior is that
software becomes less fragile so in the
code world in the code Centric World
today's reality every time you add a
feature you might break another let's
assume you do test the new feature to
make sure that it works but when you add
that feature you touch code you modify
code and you're really dependent on
these again rarely comprehensive Ive
tests to know that you haven't broken
anything else and so this is just kind
of the reality of uh of software
development today you may and you often
do break other
functionality in the spec Centric world
you make the that you define the change
that you want to the functionality of
the app in the very document that has
all the other functionality in it and so
first of all even visibly you can see
whether there are implications and when
the code gets generated every time it
gets vetted against the entirety of of
the specification and so you always know
what the application does and you are
far less likely in fact in the system
you in theory would never in practice
there's always edge cases break the
application so you always know what the
application does and that allows you to
make changes faster it allows you to
have more confidence in trying things
out versus that fearful state that you
were
before let's take it a step further like
both of those are really like the
concepts of spec Centric development so
obvious advantages let's talk about what
are the downstream implications of that
when code started getting popular new
compilers uh eventually allowed the same
codes to run on multiple platforms
multiple architectures and this was a
big unlock and a big advantage over
assembly and and really kind of felt
magical all the time because you can
have code that is portable spec Centric
development takes it to the next level
and actually takes these specs and is
able to generate software for them
across languages across Stacks you want
your JavaScript version your python
version no problem you want this on
iPhone you want this on Android that's
fine all of those do depend on some
proficiency of the system to try to
support each one of these ecosystems but
the definition of your functionality is
very much in the specification in the
validations and therefore Things become
portable this is interesting it starts
saying okay what would you do with sort
of language agnostic software how do we
think about that but it is also again
and very very uh uh flexible and
adaptable because you can use now the
software to run more sort of a secure
barebone rust environments versus more
web-based JavaScript and more you can
append to that your own context and so
the generation itself it takes that
specification but it also takes in uh
the the context that you provide to the
system about your preferences your
environments this is really where
getting to know you the equivalence of
that that I mentioned before comes into
play but it also includes how is it that
you want to describe your system are you
budget constrainted are you uh uh do you
have your own interpretations or
patterns of how you want code uh built
because of a variety of trade-offs all
of those get packaged into the context
which is can cly become quite elaborate
and to together they feed into the code
generation and you create that code and
so it really creates this adaptable
software that can adapt itself to your
needs whether it is a well-known stack
or it is something that is specific to
you adaptable software also offers what
might be the biggest advantage of AI
native software development which is
autonomous maintenance software is
always produced from that combination of
the specification and the context that
you want to generate it in and
maintenance by definition is change the
code without changing the spec I want
you to modify it so it works on this new
operating system on uh this new
dependency upgrade this uh secondary
thing or use this new service but make
the application work as it did before
because the code is always generated
from those two when a change like that
occurs as long as the platform is aware
of the context changing all you do is
you take that change you create a new
context and you create the code and the
code always always is vetted to the spec
and therefore you have assurance that
these maintenance tasks do not break the
application and in the edge cases in
which they cannot be done it surfaces it
to the user but it doesn't surprise you
and so autonomous maintenance is a huge
huge benefit because vast vast vast
majority of these changes they're not
hard changes they just require that
assurance that sort of testability
verifiability of the environment and
that ability to describe the change in
the context and by freeing up
maintenance by removing this maintenance
burden you really offload a lot of
effort from software and you allow
existing software that just continues to
run to do so without effort and you
allow developers in live systems to
spend their time creating and innovating
a closely kind of approximate to that if
we continue down that sort of Journey of
what could you do if you could verify
the functionality is you can create
better software through Auto automated
optimizations so you can take that code
and you can add agents that make it
faster that make it more secure that
make it more accessible these also
benefit from llms they also benefit from
the sort of power of look at the code
and make it better uh and you'll hear
some of that in some of the talks today
but they are uh today hard to trust
because they're unpredictable you lose
too much control they might break your
application and this this ability to
verify them to the spec opens up this
opportunity to
say attach this sequence of improvements
to my code and just make it better
always verifying it to the spec as a
result of that you can create software
that is just dramatically better imagine
an agent that every time a vulnerability
comes along it identifies it it fixes it
and it makes sure the software didn't
break that catches up to all the
compliance issues that you need to
address too and make sure the code is
modified for that to make sure that
looks for optimization opportunities and
also even is aware of new optimization
techniques to different browsers and
creates that a lot of opportunity to
make software better with a lot less
effort so this this uh opportunity to
optimize doesn't end in the build
process of it it also happens post
deployment and it can create
self-optimizing software you can take
your code that has been created from the
spec you can deploy it you can have
Telemetry and today we look at this
Telemetry and we try to learn from it so
we can improve and evolve our software
but once again that's a very expensive
process and the changes are risky so we
don't do that much I'm starting to sound
like a broken record here but the spec
centricity can help you change that you
can take that data learn something about
the system see a bottleneck of
performance for instance try to optimize
it create better better code that
addresses that bottleneck verify to the
spec and deploy it this process creates
this self-optimizing software that after
it runs it just harnesses itself it's
the same concept of what we do today
which is mature software gets better but
in a much more automated granular and
faster
fashion and this continues to sort of
similar Concepts like Dynamic software
you can create versions of the software
that are cheap at night and fast during
the day uh and even personalized
software that optimizes itself to the
user's specific needs or to a specific
environment to it all are continuations
of this adaptable
software so these are just many of the
capabilities that we can build that
really kind of tap into the power of
llms and AI thanks to this sort of spec
centricity that in turn is unlocked by
the power of AI and at the end of all of
this journey we continue go back to that
sort of core expectation and opportunity
to make software development and
software creation more inclusive much
more inclusive because indeed we level
it up to uh to the sort of ease of
creation of
language so to summarize we think AI
native development allows us to unlock
this like maximum leverage maximum ease
of Creation with a little bit of a few
words create something big but gives us
the strong controls that we need to be
able to tap into that power and this
combination is is really what we need to
be able to uh to rethink soft sare
development and make it 100 times better
versus continuing to drag along a bunch
of the problems that we're encountering
in software development today and try to
kind of patch on top of
them so this might sound somewhat
idealistic and uh and you know to an
extent it slightly is there's a lot here
uh and there's a lot to still build so
let's talk you know about a few of many
open questions uh that are here the
first one that might be obvious is what
is this magical spec that you're talking
about and how would you valid it those
are good questions we have some
theoretical answers to them and we're
working on that at tessle but we think
fundamentally there will be many ways to
specify software and there will be
multiple ways to validate it the way
that you would Define a mobile game is
not the same that you
would the way that you would specify a
mobile game uh is not the same way that
you would specify a pacemaker or a
marketing website those require
different emphasis the way you would
validate those types of software
is also similarly different right you
might need a deployed environment think
about infrastructure as code how would
you validate that so we think these are
echosystem plays and they come back to
why we think this is something that is
broader in a community
play there's also questions around how
do we deal with that software when it
misbehaves the first one is how do you
debug or observe in runtime this type of
system if you didn't write the code what
do you deal with this is not that
dissimilar to what we've seen with uh
with assembly or with sort of java B
code uh but it's still a problem that we
have to tackle say how do you understand
that there's a problem how do you get to
the root of it how do you know how to
fix it and how do you observe a running
system at this higher level of spec uh
closely related to that is a lot of the
power over here comes from this
delegation of decisions to the llm for
instance the TIC ttoe rules how do you
know that it got the TIC ttoe rules
correctly how do you know if it picked
merge sort or quicksort when do you care
and when do you not care how do you
control those degrees of freedom so we
need new methodologies around how do we
engage with the lm's decision in a way
that is that is reasonable that is not
just a magical black box that we're just
hoping that's not good enough controls
but that allows us to to interact with
the system and override decisions when
we need and promote them to the spec in
other
cases you go on to deployment and you
think about how do you even version and
package these types of adaptable
software if they become more Dynamic
this is similar to machines in the data
center versus elastic computer in the
cloud and probably the biggest question
of all is like what is the role of an AI
native developer here we think of this
as as a software creation craft we think
you're going to get better at it over
time we think uh you you have a lot to
to kind of contribute here and generally
most of the skills around software
development are still very applicable
here systems
thinking understanding of the user needs
and reducing that into what is the
solution involved of it uh a variety of
forward-looking tradeoffs all of those
are still very much needed and the best
developers today are not deemed the best
developers because they the best coders
it's about that combination of skills
but still we need to Define what is this
AI native developer how is it different
we think people will evolve up the
architect or product manager routes a
bit more use those skills more we need
to define those these reasons and more
are the reason we think of AI native
development as a new paradigm we think
of it as as a change in software
development it's like devops it's it's
like web development it is not a product
it is not a platform it is a paradigm
it's a new set of best practices and the
reason that we think this is a community
exercise and therefore in my kind of
last last slide here I want to use that
as a as a call to action for everybody
around whenever a new technology
Paradigm comes along it kind of rocks
the boat the web or or mobile or even
the personal computer and now with AI uh
it's messy it's hard to understand it it
it's different than a bunch of things
that we work with and it's easier to to
kind of grocket to to absorb it in an
opinionated closed environment this is
the system here it's working in a more
narrow fashion and so it's easier to
accept this messy new AI tenant in it uh
and and understand it within those
confines but we think that really um
doesn't allow AI to live up to its full
potential and that it's actually like a
pretty sad reality for software
development if it remains closed if the
future is you work with one of these two
three four dominant platforms and that's
the only way you develop software to an
extent like we see in Mobile we think
the future of software development
should be open and composable that many
exciting tool Builders can create pieces
of software for different stacks for
different scenarios uh that can
specialize and evolve and out innovate
and create new capabilities and that
those building software can compose
those Solutions into their environments
we think that's how AI native
development should form and so we're
investing as we said at the beginning in
AI native developer community in this
trying to create a space in which we can
Al talk about this Express opinions we
invite whether you're sort of building
tools or you're experimenting with those
tools and you want to share your
learnings or you just have opinions
about this domain come join the
conversation here share what it is that
you've learned what are your views what
is the new thing that you're proposing
on it and collaborate together to form
this view this AI native software
development
paradigm so that's it for me I hope
you're as excited about AI native
development as I am I think there's huge
potential here and I'm excited to work
with all of you in sort of shaping the
future of software development thank you
[Music]